<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-08-11T15:30:02-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Sam Rysdyk</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">How to use Git Rebase, Part II: Git Rebase Interactive</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/08/11/git-rebase-interactive.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to use Git Rebase, Part II: Git Rebase Interactive" /><published>2018-08-11T05:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-08-11T05:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/08/11/git-rebase-interactive</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/08/11/git-rebase-interactive.html">&lt;p&gt;I have previously covered Git rebase, &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/03/24/how-to-use-git-rebase.html&quot;&gt;Part I&lt;/a&gt;, but here’s another way to use it: combine commits on your branch into fewer or just one commit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a nice way to clean up git history. Frequently adding &amp;amp; committing is a good habit, but a ton of commits can really muck up a git history. Git rebase will help clean that up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Type &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;git log&lt;/code&gt; to see how far ahead feature branch B is from master branch A. Let’s say branch B has 5 commits ahead of ahead of A. By using &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;git rebase -i HEAD~5&lt;/code&gt; these 5 commits can be combined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normally, this will open up vim. However, I’ve added a command to .gitconfig to open this up in my text editor (Sublime Text, in this case), making it really easy to edit. Type this into command: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;git config --global core.editor &quot;sublime -w&quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, open up .gitconfig and add something like the following under [core]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;[core]
  editor = sublime -w
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The command is &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;git rebase -i HEAD~5&lt;/code&gt;, and -i stands for interactive mode. After submitting this, sublime text will open a file showing something like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;pick 38c1680 get bye weeks working
pick 349f80d add adp files and other updates
pick cf8bd0e fix json syntax typo
pick c7e6306 adjust styles
pick 1155626 update rankings

# Rebase e778bd6..1155626 onto e778bd6 (5 commands)
#
# Commands:
# p, pick = use commit
# r, reword = use commit, but edit the commit message
# e, edit = use commit, but stop for amending
# s, squash = use commit, but meld into previous commit
# f, fixup = like &quot;squ

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To combine these five commits, replace pick with squash like so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;pick 38c1680 get bye weeks working
squash 349f80d add adp files and other updates
squash cf8bd0e fix json syntax typo
squash c7e6306 adjust styles
squash 1155626 update rankings

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After doing this, just save and close. Then, another window should open up in Sublime Text showing commit information. Go ahead and just close that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, these 5 commits have been combined into a single commit. The commit messages from the 4 squashed commits will still be available in the commit comment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One last thing, combining commits has re-written git history. Which means it will require a force push to your remote branch: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;git push -f origin branch-b&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="code" /><summary type="html">I have previously covered Git rebase, Part I, but here’s another way to use it: combine commits on your branch into fewer or just one commit.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to really clean your postgres database</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/06/15/how-to-really-clean-your-database.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to really clean your postgres database" /><published>2018-06-15T05:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-06-15T05:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/06/15/how-to-really-clean-your-database</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/06/15/how-to-really-clean-your-database.html">&lt;p&gt;When in the course of human events it becomes necessary for one people to dissolve the outdated, conflicted, erring tables and columns, a decent respect to the opinions of mankind requires cleaning that database!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not hard to mess up a database. Git doesn’t always play nice with databases. One common situation is running a migration on one git branch, and then switching to another branch and running migrations… and surprise, there is stuff in the schema from that other branch!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While git takes care of changes to your code, it doesn’t change your underlying database. It’s important to actually read the git diff regarding the schema before committing. It is easy to include database info from some other branch! Furthermore, if you’re working on a shared code base, somebody else might check in a dirty schema and you might pull it and use before you realize what has happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is about how to (really) clean your Ruby on Rails database. Examples will be done with Rails 4, Mac terminal and Postgres. However, concepts here are general enough to work on other Rails versions and other OS and DB. It’s going to start simple and get more powerful/dangerous with each step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;step-1-fresh-schema&quot;&gt;Step 1: Fresh Schema&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is some Rails 101, but never edit the schema directly. The schema is to migrations as the gemfile.lock is to the gemfile. Just delete it and run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;rake db:migrate&lt;/code&gt; for what hopefully will be a fresh, clean copy of the schema.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is especially relevant to merge conflicts. If there’s a conflict in the schema, just delete it and migrate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;step-2-clean-setup&quot;&gt;Step 2: Clean Setup&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if your tests are looking a little funny: various things are suddenly failing even though the code related to those things hasn’t changed. Here is the simplest way to clean things up for testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;RAILS_ENV=test rake db:setup&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;RAILS_ENV=test rake test&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a combination of a three db commands:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;db:create&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;db:schema:load&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;db:seed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This should produce a clean database for testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However if that doesn’t work, perhaps something is caught in memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also worth running &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ps ax | grep spring&lt;/code&gt;. Find the number associated with the spring server (12345, for example) and run: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;kill -9 12345&lt;/code&gt;. This will help remove anything that is staying around in memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;step-3-reset&quot;&gt;Step 3: Reset&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WARNING: this will lose your data! Make sure you have a current dump (aka backup) of your data before doing this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, don’t do this unless you know what you’re doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;rake db:reset&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a combination of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;db:drop&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;db:setup&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since setup combines 3 db commands, rake db:reset is really a combination of 4 commands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point you may want to restore a backup of your data…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;step-4-rollback-migrations&quot;&gt;Step 4: Rollback Migrations&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the error has happened within the last few migration files, its simple enough to: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;rake db:rollback STEP=3&lt;/code&gt;. This will “undo” the last 3 migrations (or whatever number is specified). These migrations can now be editted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;step-5-raw-sql-in-postgres&quot;&gt;Step 5: Raw SQL in Postgres&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the above doesn’t seems to work, it might be tempting to edit old migration files. This is probably not a great idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, it might be time to manually go into Postgres and figure out what’s going on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;log into postgres from mac command line: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;psql postgres&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From here, you’ll want to see your databases: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;\l&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(that’s backslash lowercase-letter-l)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will list out all your databases. You should see the rails database that is name in config/database.yml.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From here, connect to the problematic database: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;\c database_name&lt;/code&gt;
The c is short for connect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once in here, you can list out all of the tables to see what is acutally in there: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;\dt&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This should be a list of tables that looks alot like the schema. However, it is possible that there are extra or missing tables. Running some ‘raw’ SQL can help fix this issue, without screwing with old migration files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say there are a bunch of wrong columns and we just want to completely clean it out: get rid of everything and start from scratch:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DROP SCHEMA public CASCADE;&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CREATE SCHEMA public;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;\dt&lt;/code&gt; should show there are no relations, meaning no columns. Good! We just obliberated the underlying database!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now running &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;rake db:migrate&lt;/code&gt; will install the columns created in the migration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, during this migration, there may be errors complaining that a certain column does or doesn’t exist. No problem, we can add and remove them directly in the database. Again no touching old migrations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ALTER TABLE table_name ADD COLUMN column_name type;&lt;/code&gt; or,
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ALTER TABLE table_name DROP COLUMN column_name;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, I was trying to migrate and I kept getting an error: function uuid_generate_v4() does not exist. After some googling around, I found my database needed an extension to handle UUID. Many suggested running a new migration to handle this. However, this error was happening in an old migration, so I didn’t want to screw with that. Instead we can edit. After connecting to my table, I ran:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CREATE EXTENSION &quot;uuid-ossp&quot; SCHEMA public;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boom, no more uuid_generate_v4() errors and no need to alter my old migrations or schema.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, to exit out of postgres type:
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;\q&lt;/code&gt;
to quit&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, remember the semi-colon at the end of an SQL statement, it won’t work without it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="code" /><summary type="html">When in the course of human events it becomes necessary for one people to dissolve the outdated, conflicted, erring tables and columns, a decent respect to the opinions of mankind requires cleaning that database!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Kitchen Confidential</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/06/10/kitchen-confidential.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kitchen Confidential" /><published>2018-06-10T07:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-06-10T07:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/06/10/kitchen-confidential</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/06/10/kitchen-confidential.html">&lt;p&gt;I read this book back in December 2014. I had enjoyed Bourdain’s TV shows and somewhere I read Neil Peart pay compliments to Bourdain as a writer. Having never worked in food service, and not much of a “foodie”, I was completely oblivious to the ubiquitous, if slightly underground, culture of restaurant kitchens. I had never heard of a “sous-chef” before. This book was not only educational, but very well-written. Like every great writer, Bourdain could take his specific stories and extract out universal lessons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world isn’t quite as cool without Bourdain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;= = = = =
Quotes
= = = = =&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Food had power. It could inspire, astonish, shock, excite, delight and impress. It had the power to please me . . . and others. This was valuable information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cooking is a craft, I like to think, and a good cook is a craftsman — not an artist. There’s nothing wrong with that: the great cathedrals of Europe were built by craftsmen — though not designed by them. Practicing your craft in expert fashion is noble, honorable and satisfying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good food and good eating are about risk. Every once in a while an oyster, for instance, will make you sick to your stomach. Does this mean you should stop eating oysters? No way. The more exotic the food, the more adventurous the serious eater, the higher the likelihood of later discomfort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;there are some definite dos and don’ts I’ve chosen to live by. I never order fish on Monday,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know how old most seafood is on Monday — about four to five days old!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t eat mussels in restaurants unless I know the chef personally, or have seen, with my own eyes, how they store and hold their mussels for service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brunch menus are an open invitation to the cost-conscious chef, a dumping ground for the odd bits left over from Friday and Saturday nights or for the scraps generated in the normal course of business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For ‘en vinaigrette’ on the menu, read ‘preserved’ or ‘disguised’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One other point about brunch. Cooks hate brunch. A wise chef will deploy his best line cooks on Friday and Saturday nights; he’ll be reluctant to schedule those same cooks early Sunday morning,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t eat in a restaurant with filthy bathrooms. This isn’t a hard call.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;buy up what’s left at rock-bottom prices. The next folks to arrive will be the cat-food people. Think about that when you see the ‘Discount Sushi’ sign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vegetarians, and their Hezbollah-like splinter-faction, the vegans, are a persistent irritant to any chef worth a damn. To me, life without veal stock, pork fat, sausage, organ meat, demi-glace, or even stinky cheese is a life not worth living. Vegetarians are the enemy of everything good and decent in the human spirit, an affront to all I stand for, the pure enjoyment of food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And chicken is boring. Chefs see it as a menu item for people who don’t know what they want to eat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at your waiter’s face. He knows. It’s another reason to be polite to your waiter: he could save your life with a raised eyebrow or a sigh. If he likes you, maybe he’ll stop you from ordering a piece of fish he knows is going to hurt you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He wants you to be happy on Tuesday night. On Saturday, he’s thinking more about turning over tables and getting through the rush.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like I said before, your body is not a temple, it’s an amusement park. Enjoy the ride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are, after all, citizens of the world — a world filled with bacteria, some friendly, some not so friendly. Do we really want to travel in hermetically sealed popemobiles through the rural provinces of France, Mexico and the Far East, eating only in Hard Rock Cafes and McDonald’s?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please believe me, here’s all you will ever need in the knife department: ONE good chef’s knife, as large as is comfortable for your hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;retiring their Wusthofs and replacing them with the lightweight, easy-to-sharpen and relatively inexpensive vanadium steel Global knives, a very good Japanese product which has — in addition to its many other fine qualities — the added attraction of looking really cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shallots. You almost never see this item in a home kitchen, but out in the world they’re an essential ingredient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Butter. I don’t care what they tell you they’re putting or not putting in your food at your favorite restaurant, chances are, you’re eating a ton of butter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Margarine? That’s not food. I Can’t Believe It’s Not Butter? I can. If you’re planning on using margarine in anything, you can stop reading now, because I won’t be able to help you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roasted garlic. Garlic is divine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That dried sawdust they sell in the cute little cans at the super market? You can throw that, along with the spice rack, right in the garbage. It all tastes like a stable floor. Use fresh! Good food is very often, even most often, simple food. Some of the best cuisine in the world — whole roasted fish, Tuscan-style, for instance — is a matter of three or four ingredients. Just make sure they’re good ingredients, fresh ingredients, and then garnish them. How hard is that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bigfoot understood — as I came to understand — that character is far more important than skills or employment history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior Preparation Prevents Poor Performance, as they say in the army — and I always, always want to be ready. Just like Bigfoot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a sad lesson that has served me well in decades since: I learned to recognize failure. I saw, for the first time, how two beloved, funny and popular guys can end up less beloved, not so funny and much less popular after trying to do nothing more than what their friends told them they were good at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘You know, Anthony,’ he said, ‘I have many, many enemies. It’s good, sometimes, to have enemies — even if you don’t know who they are. It means you are… important. You must be important… important enough to have an enemy.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a sous-chef with excellent cooking skills and a criminal mind is one of God’s great gifts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I appreciate people who show up every day and do the best they can, in spite of borderline personalities, substance abuse problems and anti-social tendencies; and I am often inclined to give them every opportunity to change their trajectories, to help them to arrive at a different outcome than the predictable one when they begin visibly to unravel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Be fully committed. Don’t be a fence-sitter or a waffler. If you’re going to be a chef some day, be sure about it, single-minded in your determination to achieve victory at all costs.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Learn Spanish! I can’t stress this enough.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Don’t steal. In fact, don’t do anything that you couldn’t take a polygraph test over. If you’re a chef who drinks too many freebies at the bar, takes home the occasional steak for the wife, or smokes Hawaiian bud in the off hours, be fully prepared to admit this unapologetically to any and all.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Always be on time.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Never make excuses or blame others.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Never call in sick. Except in cases of dismemberment, arterial bleeding, sucking chest wounds or the death of an immediate family member. Granny died? Bury her on your day off.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lazy, sloppy and slow are bad. Enterprising, crafty and hyperactive are good.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Be prepared to witness every variety of human folly and injustice. Without it screwing up your head or poisoning your attitude. You will simply have to endure the contradictions and inequities of this life.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Assume the worst. About everybody. But don’t let this poisoned outlook affect your job performance. Let it all roll off your back. Ignore it. Be amused by what you see and suspect. Just because someone you work with is a miserable, treacherous, self-serving, capricious and corrupt asshole shouldn’t prevent you from enjoying their company, working with them or finding them entertaining.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Try not to lie.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forgot to place the produce order? Don’t lie about it. You made a mistake. Admit it and move on. Just don’t do it again. Ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Avoid restaurants where the owner’s name is over the door. Avoid restaurants that smell bad. Avoid restaurants with names that will look funny or pathetic on your resume.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Think about that resume! How will it look to the chef weeding through a stack of faxes if you’ve never worked in one place longer than six months?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Read! Read cookbooks, trade magazines — I recommend Food Arts, Saveur, Restaurant Business magazines.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some awareness of the history of your business is useful, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have a sense of humor about things. You’ll need it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Anthony Bourdain</name></author><summary type="html">I read this book back in December 2014. I had enjoyed Bourdain’s TV shows and somewhere I read Neil Peart pay compliments to Bourdain as a writer. Having never worked in food service, and not much of a “foodie”, I was completely oblivious to the ubiquitous, if slightly underground, culture of restaurant kitchens. I had never heard of a “sous-chef” before. This book was not only educational, but very well-written. Like every great writer, Bourdain could take his specific stories and extract out universal lessons.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bootstrap Grid by Example: How to use containers, rows, columns</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/04/30/bootstrap-grid-containers-rows-columns.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bootstrap Grid by Example: How to use containers, rows, columns" /><published>2018-04-30T05:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-04-30T05:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/04/30/bootstrap-grid-containers-rows-columns</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/04/30/bootstrap-grid-containers-rows-columns.html">&lt;p&gt;There is a lot of poorly written bootstrap out there. Much of it revolves around the most fundamental aspect of boostrap: the grid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a basic guide to the Bootstrap grid, mostly for Bootstrap v3, but also applicable to v4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-grid&quot;&gt;The Grid&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there are three fundamental elements:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;containers&lt;/strong&gt;: container and container-fluid. Container will only expand to a max-width, while container-fluid will go to full width of screen. Container should never be nest inside other containers.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;rows&lt;/strong&gt;: A row is a column wrapper. Without columns, no need for a row.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;columns&lt;/strong&gt;: to divide content into 2 or more horizontal sections. Columns should typically be directly need inside a row. A single column doesn’t need to be a column at all. Columns are mobile-first.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;bootstrap-grid-examples&quot;&gt;Bootstrap grid examples:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;example-1&quot;&gt;Example 1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;!-- anti-pattern --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;container-fluid&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;row&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;content!&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;row&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;col-xs-12&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;more content!&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;!-- instead --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;container-fluid&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;content!&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;more content!&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;example-2&quot;&gt;Example 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;!-- anti-pattern --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;container-fluid&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;col-sm-6&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;row&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;content!&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;col-sm-6&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;row&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;more content!&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;!-- instead --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;container-fluid&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;row&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;col-sm-6&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;content!&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;col-sm-6&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;more content!&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;example-3&quot;&gt;Example 3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;!-- anti-pattern --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;body&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;col-sm-6&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;content!&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;col-sm-6&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;more content!&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;!-- instead --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;body&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;container-fluid&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;row&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;col-sm-6&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;content!&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;col-sm-6&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;more content!&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;example-4&quot;&gt;Example 4&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;!-- anti-pattern --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;container-fluid&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;row&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;col-xs-12 col-sm-12 col-md-6 col-lg-6&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;content!&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;col-xs-12 col-sm-12 col-md-6 col-lg-6&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;more content!&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;!-- instead --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;container-fluid&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;row&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;col-md-6&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;content!&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;col-md-6&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;more content!&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;example-5&quot;&gt;Example 5&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;!-- anti-pattern --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;container-fluid&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;row&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;container&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;col-md-6&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;row&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
                    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;content!&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;col-xs-12 col-sm-12 col-md-6 col-lg-6&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;more content!&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;!-- instead --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;container-fluid&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;row&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;col-md-6&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;content!&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;col-md-6&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;more content!&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;full-width-bg-example&quot;&gt;Full-Width BG Example&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full-width backgrounds are popular in web-design. Here’s a common situation where the header and footer and full width:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;header&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;full-width-bg&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;container-fluid&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;row&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;col-md-3&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;Title!&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;col-md-9&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;more content!&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/header&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;section&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;full-width-bg&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;container-fluid&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;row&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;col-md-6&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;content!&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;col-md-6&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;more content!&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/section&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;section&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;full-width-bg&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;container-fluid&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;row&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;col-md-6&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;content!&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;col-md-6&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;more content!&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/section&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;footer&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;full-width-bg&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;container-fluid&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;row&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;col-md-4&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;content!&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;col-md-4&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;more content!&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;col-md-4&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;more content!&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/footer&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="code" /><summary type="html">There is a lot of poorly written bootstrap out there. Much of it revolves around the most fundamental aspect of boostrap: the grid.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Use Git Rebase</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/03/24/how-to-use-git-rebase.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Use Git Rebase" /><published>2018-03-24T07:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-03-24T07:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/03/24/how-to-use-git-rebase</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/03/24/how-to-use-git-rebase.html">&lt;p&gt;When starting out with git, rebase is scary because it’s often not explained well, but it’s really not that hard. It’s important to understand rebase because it should be a regular tool used with git.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are few different ways to use rebase, but here’s the basic concept of git rebase: &lt;strong&gt;to keep your branch up-to-date with its parent branch&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, feature branch B is created off of master branch A:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Master A:  [1] - - - [2]
                                    \  
                                       \
Feature B:                       [3]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, feature B is &lt;em&gt;based on&lt;/em&gt; master A at commit 2. The point where they split, Commit 2, is B’s base. To ‘rebase’ is to update/move where this split happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While working on feature B, you checkout master and pull from origin master to find other developers have committed new code to master A. The situation now looks something like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Master A:  [1] - - - [2] - - - [4] - - - [5] - - - [6]
                                   \  
                                      \
Feature B:                     [3] - - - [7]    
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without rebase, when B is merged back into A there can be a ton of conflicts since many things have changed on A as B was being worked. Fixing all these conflicts all at once at the time of merge can be tedious and error-prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, it’s a good idea to make sure your feature branch is still relevant to master as you’re working on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if a developer could incorporate the changes of Master A into Feature B on a regular basis as B is being worked on? This is rebase!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While on branch B, type: ‘git rebase A’. This is rebasing B &lt;em&gt;onto&lt;/em&gt; A. This moves B’s base from 2 to 6, thus incorporating commits 4, 5 and 6 into B.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Master A:  [1] - - - [2] - - - [4] - - - [5] - - - [6]
                                                                        \  
                                                                           \
Feature B:                                                          [3] - - - [7]             
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now feature B is all caught up. (Any code conflicts can be handled now and how to do this will be the subject of a future post).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nice thing about rebase is that it can be used as often as needed. If you know master has been updated, pull the changes and rebase. Or simply get in the daily habit of using rebase every morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A morning routine might look like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;git checkout master
git pull origin master
git checkout feature_branch
git rebase master
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The terminology of ‘off of’, ‘onto’ and ‘into’ can get confusing, but it goes like this: rebasing B &lt;em&gt;onto&lt;/em&gt; A brings the new part(s) of A &lt;em&gt;into&lt;/em&gt; B.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important to note that rebasing can get a little tricky when working with remote branches. After rebasing feature B onto master A, a force push may be required if feature B has a remote git repository. The golden rule of force pushing is never force push to a public repo: if anybody else is sharing feature B, avoid force pushing. In general, don’t use force push unless you’re fairly sure about what you’re doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the basic concept of git rebase!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="code" /><summary type="html">When starting out with git, rebase is scary because it’s often not explained well, but it’s really not that hard. It’s important to understand rebase because it should be a regular tool used with git.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Boys in the Boat</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/03/24/the-boys-in-the-boat.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Boys in the Boat" /><published>2018-03-24T07:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-03-24T07:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/03/24/the-boys-in-the-boat</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/03/24/the-boys-in-the-boat.html">&lt;p&gt;Great Book. Had I read this as a high school rower, I would’ve been applying to the University of Washington and their rowing team. The book has multiple narratives, but the two main stories are that of Hitler/Nazi Germany as they geared up in the 1930s and rower Joe Rantz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The author could have picked any of the eight rowers in the ‘36 Olympic boat to serve as the main protagonist, but Joe Rantz’s story is incredible: abandoned by his family (the mean step-mother…) as a teenager, Rantz managed to somehow survive, get invited to the university rowing team, make the varsity boat, and then win Olympic gold in front of Hitler. None of this is really spoiler information; the details of this incredible story that make the book worth reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book also covers The Great Depression, the Dust Bowl, the New Deal, the second World War. Seattle is now one of the great cities in this country, but in the 1920s and 30s it was consider very backwoods by the rest of the country. A rowing team from Seattle was a real long shot back then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was fortuitous timing to have read this durint this year’s Winter Olympics. Some real parallels with today’s events: the Olympics are more than just an atheletic competition, there very real political and historical undertones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;= = = = =
Quotes
= = = = =&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a sport like this—hard work, not much glory, but still popular in every century—well, there must be some beauty which ordinary men can’t see, but extraordinary men do. — George Yeoman Pocock&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;but rowing—he understood as well as anyone—was at least as much art as brawn, and a keen intelligence was just as important as brute strength.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trick would be to find which few of them had the potential for raw power, the nearly superhuman stamina, the indomitable willpower, and the intellectual capacity necessary to master the details of technique. And which of them, coupled improbably with all those other qualities, had the most important one: the ability to disregard his own ambitions, to throw his ego over the gunwales, to leave it swirling in the wake of his shell, and to pull, not just for himself, not just for glory, but for the other boys in the boat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Competitive rowing is an undertaking of extraordinary beauty preceded by brutal punishment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Nobody ever took time out in a boat race,”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;your body burns calories and consumes oxygen at a rate that is unmatched in almost any other human endeavor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Physiologists, in fact, have calculated that rowing a two-thousand-meter race—the Olympic standard—takes the same physiological toll as playing two basketball games back-to-back. And it exacts that toll in about six minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pound for pound, Olympic oarsmen may take in and process as much oxygen as a thoroughbred racehorse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not a question of whether you will hurt, or of how much you will hurt; it’s a question of what you will do, and how well you will do it, while pain has her wanton way with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and that by Christmas break most of them would have given up, perhaps to play something less physically and intellectually demanding, like football.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;George Yeoman Pocock was all but born with an oar in his hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“No one will ask you how long it took to build; they will only ask who built it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conibear—who would come to be called the father of Washington rowing—had become Washington’s coach because nobody else was available to take the job, not because he knew the first thing about rowing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is hard to make that boat go as fast as you want to. The enemy, of course, is resistance of the water, as you have to displace the amount of water equal to the weight of men and equipment, but that very water is what supports you and that very enemy is your friend. So is life: the very problems you must overcome also support you and make you stronger in overcoming them. —George Yeoman Pocock&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;it wasn’t a matter of luck at all, that it was just a matter of keeping your eyes open. “The only time you don’t find a four-leaf clover,” he liked to say, “is when you stop looking for one.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the fundamental challenges in rowing is that when any one member of a crew goes into a slump the entire crew goes with him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the demands of rowing are such that every man or woman in a racing shell depends on his or her crewmates to perform almost flawlessly with each and every pull of the oar. The movements of each rower are so intimately intertwined, so precisely synchronized with the movements of all the others, that any one rower’s mistake or subpar performance can throw off the tempo of the stroke, the balance of the boat, and ultimately the success of the whole crew. More often than not, it comes down to a lack of concentration on one person’s part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the rest of the boat necessarily goes where the bow goes, any deflection or irregularity in the stroke of the oarsman in the bow seat has the greatest potential to disrupt the course, speed, and stability of the boat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The four, five, and six seats are often called “the engine room” of the crew, and the rowers who occupy these seats are typically the biggest and strongest in the boat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The speed of a racing shell is determined primarily by two factors: the power produced by the combined strokes of the oars, and the stroke rate,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A boat with both a very high stroke rate and very powerful strokes will beat a boat that can’t match it on both counts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You had to master your opponent mentally. When the critical moment in a close race was upon you, you had to know something he did not—that down in your core you still had something in reserve, something you had not yet shown, something that once revealed would make him doubt himself, make him falter just when it counted the most. Like so much in life, crew was partly about confidence, partly about knowing your own heart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the second decade of the new century, tens of thousands of fans—as many as 125,000 in 1929—came to Poughkeepsie to watch the annual regatta in person; millions more listened to the radio coverage; and the regatta came to rival the Kentucky Derby, the Rose Bowl, and the World Series as a major national sporting event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 1934 regatta was once again shaping up to be a clash of eastern privilege and prestige on the one hand and western sincerity and brawn on the other. In financial terms, it was pretty starkly going to be a clash of old money versus no money at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You will eat no fried meats,” he began abruptly. “You will eat no pastries, but you will eat plenty of vegetables. You will eat good, substantial, wholesome food—the kind of food your mother makes. You will go to bed at ten o’clock and arise punctually at seven o’clock. You will not smoke or drink or chew. And you will follow this regimen all year round, for as long as you row for me. A man cannot abuse his body for six months and then expect to row the other six months. He must be a total abstainer all year. You will not use profane language in the shell house, nor anywhere within my hearing. You will keep at your studies and maintain a high grade point average. You will not disappoint your parents, nor your crewmates. Now let’s row.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She told Harry to get out of the house, and not to come back until he had a job. Harry headed for Los Angeles. Six months later, he returned with a motorcycle but no job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It takes energy to get angry. It eats you up inside. I can’t waste my energy like that and expect to get ahead. When they left, it took everything I had in me just to survive. Now I have to stay focused. I’ve just gotta take care of it myself.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;George Pocock was already building the best, and doing so by a wide margin. He didn’t just build racing shells. He sculpted them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Partly, it was because he could not abide the noise that power tools made. Craftsmanship required thought, and thought required a quiet environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a thing that sometimes happens in rowing that is hard to achieve and hard to define. Many crews, even winning crews, never really find it. Others find it but can’t sustain it. It’s called “swing.” It only happens when all eight oarsmen are rowing in such perfect unison that no single action by any one is out of synch with those of all the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stroke rate is one thing and power is another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the faster the boat goes, the harder it is to row well. The enormously complicated sequence of movements, each of which an oarsman must execute with exquisite precision, becomes exponentially more difficult to perform as the stroke rate increases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put another way, beautiful and effective rowing often means painful rowing. An unnamed coach is reputed to have said, bluntly, “Rowing is like a beautiful duck. On the surface it is all grace, but underneath the bastard’s paddling like mad!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sport offers so many opportunities for suffering and so few opportunities for glory that only the most tenaciously self-reliant and self-motivated are likely to succeed at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great crews may have men or women of exceptional talent or strength; they may have outstanding coxswains or stroke oars or bowmen; but they have no stars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if they could, few rowing coaches would simply clone their biggest, strongest, smartest, and most capable rowers. Crew races are not won by clones. They are won by crews, and great crews are carefully balanced blends of both physical abilities and personality types.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good crews are good blends of personalities: someone to lead the charge, someone to hold something in reserve; someone to pick a fight, someone to make peace; someone to think things through, someone to charge ahead without thinking. Somehow all this must mesh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Sure, I can make a boat,” he said, and then added, quoting the poet Joyce Kilmer, “‘But only God can make a tree.’”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ability to yield, to bend, to give way, to accommodate, he said, was sometimes a source of strength in men as well as in wood, so long as it was helmed by inner resolve and by principle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said for him the craft of building a boat was like religion. It wasn’t enough to master the technical details of it. You had to give yourself up to it spiritually; you had to surrender yourself absolutely to it. When you were done and walked away from the boat, you had to feel that you had left a piece of yourself behind in it forever, a bit of your heart. He turned to Joe. “Rowing,” he said, “is like that. And a lot of life is like that too, the parts that really matter anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like most competitive rowers, he was drawn to difficult things. A good challenge had always interested him, appealed to him. That was, in many ways, why he rowed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When eight very large men are in constant motion in a twenty-four-inch-wide vessel and the wind is blowing and the tide or current is relentlessly trying to push them off course, steering is no small challenge. But it’s the least of what a coxswain must worry about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, a good coxswain is a quarterback, a cheerleader, and a coach all in one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He suggested that Joe think of a well-rowed race as a symphony, and himself as just one player in the orchestra. If one fellow in an orchestra was playing out of tune, or playing at a different tempo, the whole piece would naturally be ruined. That’s the way it was with rowing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And he concluded with a remark that Joe would never forget. “Joe, when you really start trusting those other boys, you will feel a power at work within you that is far beyond anything you’ve ever imagined. Sometimes, you will feel as if you have rowed right off the planet and are rowing among the stars.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Increasing numbers of people in Europe and the United States were beginning to talk again about Germany, as they had during the First World War, when it had generally been seen as a nation of “Huns,” of lawless barbarians. Hitler knew it would be much easier for the West to mobilize against a nation of barbarians than a civilized nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Nazi leadership was now convinced that the upcoming Olympic Games, in August, would provide the perfect opportunity for a masquerade. Germany would present herself to the world as an unusually clean, efficient, modern, technologically savvy, cultured, vigorous, reasonable, and hospitable nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therein lies the secret of successful crews: Their “swing,” that fourth dimension of rowing, which can only be appreciated by an oarsman who has rowed in a swinging crew, where the run is uncanny and the work of propelling the shell a delight. —George Yeoman Pocock&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good thoughts have much to do with good rowing. It isn’t enough for the muscles of a crew to work in unison; their hearts and minds must also be as one. —George Yeoman Pocock&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harmony, balance, and rhythm. They’re the three things that stay with you your whole life. Without them civilization is out of whack. And that’s why an oarsman, when he goes out in life, he can fight it, he can handle life. That’s what he gets from rowing. —George Yeoman Pocock&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the race, the sagest and most ancient among Al Ulbrickson’s peers, old Jim Ten Eyck of Syracuse, finally said flat out what he’d been thinking about the Washington varsity boat for some time: “It’s the greatest eight I ever saw, and I never expect to see another like it.” Coming from a man who had watched crews come and go since 1861, it was quite a statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;in four years of college rowing, each of them had rowed approximately 4,344 miles, far enough to take him from Seattle to Japan. Along the way, each had taken roughly 469,000 strokes with his oar, all in preparation for only 28 miles of actual collegiate racing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Daniel James Brown</name></author><summary type="html">Great Book. Had I read this as a high school rower, I would’ve been applying to the University of Washington and their rowing team. The book has multiple narratives, but the two main stories are that of Hitler/Nazi Germany as they geared up in the 1930s and rower Joe Rantz.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mac Terminal Setup</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/02/10/mac-terminal-setup.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mac Terminal Setup" /><published>2018-02-10T06:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-02-10T06:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/02/10/mac-terminal-setup</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/02/10/mac-terminal-setup.html">&lt;p&gt;Here are a few quick things to make working in Mac’s Terminal with Rails and Git a little better:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#aliases&quot;&gt;Aliases&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#quick-jump&quot;&gt;Quick Jump Between Folders&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#display-git-branch&quot;&gt;Display Current Git Branch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#git-tab-completion&quot;&gt;Add Git Branch Completion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of these things involve downloading some stuff and then updating the .bash_profile or .bashrc. To open those, in terminal type: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;open ~/.bashrc&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;open ~/.bash_profile&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;aliases&quot;&gt;Aliases&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aliases are shortcuts for things commonly typed into terminal: instead of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;rails console&lt;/code&gt;, just use &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;rc&lt;/code&gt; and instead of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;git push origin master&lt;/code&gt;, just &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;gpom&lt;/code&gt;. It’s nice to avoid typing the same things over and over again, especially if it’s easy to make a typo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;gdm&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;olm&lt;/code&gt; are two of my particular favorites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No Homebrew needed here. Just setup aliases like these in .bashrc:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;alias m=&quot;mate .&quot;
alias o=&quot;open .&quot;
alias s=&quot;sublime .&quot;
alias a=&quot;atom .&quot;

  # git aliases
alias gl=&quot;git pull&quot;
alias gc=&quot;git checkout&quot;
alias gp=&quot;git push&quot;
alias gpom=&quot;git push origin master&quot;
alias gb=&quot;git branch&quot;
alias gs=&quot;git status&quot;
alias gaa=&quot;git add .&quot;
alias gr=&quot;git rebase&quot;
alias grc=&quot;git rebase --continue&quot;
alias gri=&quot;git rebase -i&quot;
alias gcm=&quot;git commit -m&quot;
alias gd=&quot;git diff&quot;
 # open all files with git conflicts in textmate
alias gdm=&quot;git diff --name-only | uniq | xargs mate&quot;
alias glg=&quot;git log&quot;


  # rails related aliases
alias rc=&quot;rails console&quot;
alias rs=&quot;rails server&quot;
alias rdbm=&quot;rake db:migrate&quot;
alias rdbs=&quot;rake db:seed&quot;
alias renvt=&quot;RAILS_ENV=test&quot;
alias rt=&quot;rake test&quot;
alias be=&quot;bundle exec&quot;
alias bi=&quot;bundle install&quot;
alias bu=&quot;bundle update&quot;
 # open last migration in textmate
alias olm=&quot;ls db/migrate/* | tail -n1 | xargs mate&quot;

alias js=&quot;jekyll serve&quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ensure .bashrc is referenced in .bash_profile. At or near the top of .bash_profile include this line: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;source ~/.bashrc  # get my Bash aliases&lt;/code&gt;. Also, .bashrc is really picky about formatting, the alias needs to touch the equals sign which needs to touch the opening double quote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once this is updated, start a new terminal session or use &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;source ~/.bash_profile&lt;/code&gt; in the current session to make the new aliases available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;quick-jump&quot;&gt;Quick Jump&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quick jump between folders is a game-changer. From within one app, navigate directly to another non-linear folder or even another app without changing directory up and down multiple levels!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, use &lt;a href=&quot;https://brew.sh&quot;&gt;Homebrew&lt;/a&gt; to install bash completion: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;brew install bash-completion&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add the following code to .bash_profile:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;if [ -f $(brew --prefix)/etc/bash_completion ]; then
. $(brew --prefix)/etc/bash_completion
fi&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then in .bashrc:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;PROJ_DIR=&quot;~/Work&quot;
ORDERED_SUBFOLDERS=&quot;app1 app2 app3 app4 app5&quot;

CDPATH=&quot;.:~:$PROJ_DIR&quot;
for FOLDER in $ORDERED_SUBFOLDERS; do
  CDPATH=&quot;$CDPATH:$PROJ_DIR/$FOLDER&quot;
done&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this example, PROJ_DIR will be the main folder (it could be anything). Then specify the subfolders, whatever those are. Restart terminal, and cd between app projects without navigating up and down directories one at a time. Folders within the sub folders will be available to quick jump to as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;display-git-branch&quot;&gt;Display Git Branch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s nice to see which branch we’re working on. To display the current git branch in terminal, place this code in .bash_profile:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;parse_git_branch() {
     git branch 2&amp;gt; /dev/null | sed -e '/^[^*]/d' -e 's/* \(.*\)/ (\1)/'
}
export PS1=&quot;\u@\h \[\033[32m\]\w\[\033[33m\]\$(parse_git_branch)\[\033[00m\] $ &quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;git-tab-completion&quot;&gt;Git Tab Completion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like terminal will try to auto-compelete folder and file names with tab, we can add the same thing for git branch names. Just type the first few letters of a branch name and tab to complete it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Install git-completion via curl command: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;curl https://raw.githubusercontent.com/git/git/master/contrib/completion/git-completion.bash -o ~/.git-completion.bash&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then add the following to .bashrc:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;if [ -f ~/.git-completion.bash ]; then
  . ~/.git-completion.bash

  # Add git completion to aliases
  __git_complete gc _git_checkout
  __git_complete gl _git_pull
  __git_complete gp _git_push
  __git_complete gb _git_branch
fi&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Restart terminal or re-source the .bash_profile. Not only does this work with regular typed out git commands, but it will work with aliases as well.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="code" /><summary type="html">Here are a few quick things to make working in Mac’s Terminal with Rails and Git a little better: Aliases Quick Jump Between Folders Display Current Git Branch Add Git Branch Completion</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Simple Responsive SCSS Grid</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/01/20/simple-scss-responsive-grid.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Simple Responsive SCSS Grid" /><published>2018-01-20T06:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-01-20T06:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/01/20/simple-scss-responsive-grid</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/01/20/simple-scss-responsive-grid.html">&lt;p&gt;CSS grids are great, but a whole framework (Bootstrap, Foundation, etc) for a simple grid is unnecessary – many mbs and thousands of lines of code for a little organization and responsiveness?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a simple grid I’ve been using in a few lines of scss:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-scss&quot; data-lang=&quot;scss&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// grid.scss
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;@mixin&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;clearfix&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nd&quot;&gt;:before&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nd&quot;&gt;:after&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;nl&quot;&gt;clear&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;both&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;nl&quot;&gt;content&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;nl&quot;&gt;display&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;block&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;.container&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nl&quot;&gt;margin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;auto&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nl&quot;&gt;width&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;90%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;@include&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nd&quot;&gt;clearfix&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;.row&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nl&quot;&gt;display&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;block&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;@include&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nd&quot;&gt;clearfix&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;@mixin&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;columns&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nl&quot;&gt;box-sizing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;border-box&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nl&quot;&gt;float&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;left&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nl&quot;&gt;padding&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;10px&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nl&quot;&gt;width&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;100%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

	&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;@media&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;screen&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;min-width&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;700px&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;nl&quot;&gt;width&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;100%&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here is how it’s used:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;!-- page.html --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;container&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;row&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;className&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;className&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;className&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-scss&quot; data-lang=&quot;scss&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// stylesheet.scss (with grid imported)
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;.className&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;@include&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nd&quot;&gt;columns&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Done. Mobile-first, responsive columns. Above 700px (or whatever is specified) div.className becomes 3 columns and below it’s one column.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A sidenote: keeping up with different device widths and pixel densities isn’t sustainable. I’ve found it’s fine to set one or two breakpoints where the structure of the page can dramatically change; meanwhile, the content is always responsive within those breakpoints. Everything is responsive, yet simple and device agnostic. More on this idea: &lt;a href=&quot;https://adamsilver.io/articles/stop-using-device-breakpoints/&quot;&gt;Stop Using Device Breakpoints&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s trivial to set up multiple breakpoints:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-scss&quot; data-lang=&quot;scss&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$screen-md&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;900px&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$screen-lg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;1200px&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;.className&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;@include&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nd&quot;&gt;columns&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;6&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;@media&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;screen&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;min-width&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$screen-md&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;@include&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nd&quot;&gt;columns&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;@media&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;screen&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;min-width&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$screen-lg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;@include&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nd&quot;&gt;columns&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only is this simple, it’s also semantic! No need to bloat the html with column classes: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div class=&quot;className col-xs-12 col-sm-6 col-md-3 col-lg-2&quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;. Styling stays in the styling - what a concept!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="code" /><summary type="html">CSS grids are great, but a whole framework (Bootstrap, Foundation, etc) for a simple grid is unnecessary – many mbs and thousands of lines of code for a little organization and responsiveness?!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Happy City</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/10/01/happy_cities.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Happy City" /><published>2017-10-01T07:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-10-01T07:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2017/10/01/happy_cities</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2017/10/01/happy_cities.html">&lt;p&gt;I read this book just after reading Walkable City. Both of these have served as my introduction to urbanism and city planning. In addition to city planning this book is more broadly about human happiness and economics. In the United States, “economic growth” is dogma. Many believe the end of economic growth justify the means. But what is the point of economic growth if people generally unhappier and unhealthier? What if short-term econonomic growth in a quarter-by-quarter economy comes at the expense of long-term economic growth?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;= = = = =
Quotes
= = = = =&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dream of riches, Peñalosa complained, served only to make Bogotans feel bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peñalosa promised neither a car in every garage nor a socialist revolution. His promise was simple. He was going to make Bogotans happier. “And what are our needs for happiness?” he asked. “We need to walk, just as birds need to fly. We need to be around other people. We need beauty. We need contact with nature. And most of all, we need not to be excluded. We need to feel some sort of equality.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a gospel of transformative urbanism. The city itself could be a device for happiness. Life could be improved, even amid economic doldrums, by changing the shapes and systems that defined urban existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peñalosa’s first and most defining act as mayor was to declare war: not on crime or drugs or poverty, but on private cars. “A city can be friendly to people or it can be friendly to cars, but it can’t be both,” he announced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the third year of his term Peñalosa challenged Bogotans to participate in an experiment, a día sin carro. As of dawn on February 24, 2000, all private cars were banned from city streets for the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was the first day in four years that nobody was killed in traffic. Hospital admissions fell by almost a third. The toxic haze over the city thinned. People still got to work, and schools reported normal attendance. Bogotans enjoyed the day so much that they voted to make it a yearly affair, and to ban all private cars during rush hour every day by 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The urban shake-up that began with the mortgage crisis in 2008 hit the newest, shiniest, most sprawling parts of the American city the hardest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sprawl city requires cheap energy, cheap land, and cheap materials, and the days of cheap are over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A man could achieve pure happiness only by reaching the height of his potential, and that meant not just thinking virtuously but behaving virtuously too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adam Smith warned that it was a deception to believe that wealth and comfort alone would bring happiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He found that people who claimed to be happy tended to have more blood flowing to that left prefrontal region than to the right side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of all the ways they passed their days, having sex made the women happiest of all, with socializing coming a close second. What made them least happy? Commuting to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside Disneyland, even today, every architectural detail, every view, every transportation experience, every sensation—right down to the texture of the pavement and the scent of the air—was designed with the express purpose of tipping the hedonic scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are left with the question of authenticity: If you’re happy, does reality matter?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People who are well educated rate their happiness higher than those who aren’t. Employed people are happier than unemployed people—&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life satisfaction is strongly influenced by location.* People in small towns are generally happier than people who live in big cities. People who live next to the ocean report being happier than those who don’t. Living under the flight path of commuter jets is terrible for happiness. Persistent wind is bad, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;when it comes to life satisfaction, relationships with other people beat income, hands down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just going from being friendless to having one friend or family member to confide in had the same effect on life satisfaction as a tripling of income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our trust in neighbors, police, governments, and even total strangers has a huge influence on happiness—again, much more than income does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;cities must be regarded as more than engines of wealth; they must be viewed as systems that should be shaped to improve human well-being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For every new urban plaza, starchitect-designed tower, or sleek new light-rail network, there are a hundred thousand cul-de-sacs out in the dispersed city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, the dispersed city is the most expensive, resource-intense, land-gobbling, polluting way of living ever built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The average exurban family needs at least one more car than do families who live close to where they work, shop, study, and play. That family also spends twice as much just getting around in order to meet its daily needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(It’s also a reason that the farther a house was from a vibrant city center, the more likely it was to experience foreclosure during the crash,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investing in a detached home on the urban edge is like gambling on oil futures and global geopolitics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As much as we complain about other people, there is nothing worse for mental health than a social desert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;cities. A Swedish study found that people who endure more than a forty-five-minute commute were 40 percent more likely to divorce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People’s new homes were so big that they created a whole new layer of housekeeping, and so expensive that they forced their owners to work harder to keep them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans do not perceive the value of things in absolute terms. We never have. Just as our eyes process the color and luminosity of an object relative to its surroundings, the brain constantly adjusts its idea of what we need in order to be happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have been hardwired for active dissatisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, Stutzer and Frey found that a person with a one-hour commute has to earn 40 percent more money to be as satisfied with life as someone who walks to the office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quick: Which would make you happier—living in California or the U.S. Midwest?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Californians and midwesterners report pretty much the same level of life satisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest danger is, by its nature, the least exciting. It is the sickness that comes from doing nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;aside from sedentary Saudi Arabians and some South Pacific Islanders, Americans are now the fattest people on the planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;killer drivers are so common in sprawl that the carnage they create far exceeds the damage done by killers who use other weapons. In fact, someone who walks out her door on the edges of sprawl suburbia is much more likely to die at the hands of a stranger than someone moving through most American central cities or inner suburbs. The only difference is that most of suburbia’s killers didn’t mean it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s an image that sticks: imagine a loaded Boeing 747 crashing every three days, killing everyone aboard. That’s how many people die on U.S. highways every year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;rational actor would be terrified of suburban roads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result: drivers kill four times as many pedestrians on spacious suburban residential streets than on the narrow streets of traditional neighborhoods, because those spacious roads make driving faster feel safer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is not collisions that kill people, but collisions at high speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A pedestrian hit by a car going 35 miles per hour is ten times as likely to die than if he was hit by a car going 25 miles per hour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The average time it takes for new urban highway capacity to fill up with new demand? Five to six years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are using so much of the earth’s raw material that we are dooming future generations to poverty and hardship. It would take nine planets to supply all we needed if everyone ate, built, traveled, and threw stuff away as Americans do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On average, suburbanites pump out about twice the greenhouse gas emissions of people living in dense city centers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;people who live in areas with more parks are more helpful and trusting than people who don’t, regardless of their income or race. Nature is not merely good for us. It brings out the good in us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is crucial for healthy living, she insists, is not quantity, but regular exposure, daily doses of nature. So the trick is in finding ways to infuse nature, and nature complexity, into denser places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That made Vancouver the only major city in North America without a single highway running through its core.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of what made Vancouver’s vertical experiment both unique and desirable was the way it accommodated residents’ biophilic needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One big park won’t do. “We can’t just build Central Park and say, ‘Well, we’re done,’” Kuo insisted. “Nature has to be part of your life. It has to be part of your daily habitat and routine.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you search hard enough for places that balance our competing needs for privacy, nature, conviviality, and convenience, you end up with a hybrid, somewhere between the vertical and horizontal city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the Second World War, the capital of Denmark had embraced dispersal as fervently as any American city. Everyone bought a car, and suburbs spilled out from the city’s medieval heart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We found that if you make more road space, you get more cars. If you make more bike lanes, you get more bikes. If you make more space for people, you get more people and of course then you get public life.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tellingly, the word community is increasingly used to refer to groups of people who use the same media or who happen to like a certain product, regardless of whether its members have actually met.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Television, that great window to the world, has been an unequivocal disaster for happiness. The more TV you watch, the fewer friendships you are likely to have, the less trusting you become, and the less happy you are likely to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;every urban landscape is a collection of memory- and emotion-activating symbols.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Human bones have evolved to withstand impact with hard surfaces up to a speed of about twenty miles per hour, which is faster than a reasonably fit person can run.* So it is natural to get anxious when confronted with hard objects moving faster than that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Participants begin to ask what streets are for, and they invariably seize upon the answer that Copenhageners found decades ago: streets are for whatever we decide they are for, and central cities need not accept the discomforts thrust on them by dispersal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No wonder four in ten Americans actually claim to love their cars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One group of commuters reports enjoying themselves more than everyone else. Their route to happy mobility is simple. These are people who travel on their own steam like Robert Judge. They walk. They run. They ride bicycles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why would traveling more slowly and using more effort offer more satisfaction than driving? Part of the answer exists in basic human physiology. We were born to move—not merely to be transported,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The psychologist has devoted his life to the study of human moods. In test after test he proved that the most powerful way to fix a dark mood is simply to take a brisk walk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can literally walk ourselves into a state of well-being. The same is true of cycling,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bicycle can expand the self-propelled travelers’ geographical reach by an astounding nine or sixteen times. Quite simply, a human on a bicycle is the most efficient traveler among all machines and animals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Few places design travel behavior as powerfully as Atlanta. The average working adult in Atlanta’s suburbs now drives forty-four miles a day.† Ninety-four percent of Atlantans commute by car.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surveys in the United States and Canada reveal that transit riders are the most miserable commuters of all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s just that decades of underinvestment mean that the typical transit journey is crowded, slow, uncertain, or uncomfortable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;administrators typically choose the most utilitarian-looking materials for bus interiors and stations—even when attractive finishes are no more expensive—simply to avoid the appearance of having wasted money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Geller and his colleagues set out to create a network of “low-stress” bikeways that either physically separated cyclists from cars or slowed cars down past the speed of fear on shared routes. It worked. Commuting by bike more than doubled in Portland between 2000 and 2008.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is where equity and efficiency collide: because of their light footprint, infrastructure for walkers and cyclists costs only a tiny fraction of auto infrastructure to build and maintain. So cyclists and pedestrian commuters who pay property and income tax actually end up subsidizing their car-driving neighbors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the fair city, people who share space on transit enjoy the right-of-way on congested roads. In the fair city, streets are safe for everyone, especially children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the fair city, everyone has access to parks, shops, services, and healthy food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The happy city plan is an energy plan. It is a climate plan. It is a belt-tightening plan for cash-strapped cities. It is also an economic plan, a jobs plan, and a corrective for weak systems. It is a plan for resilience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I realized that the power that shapes our city is in the code, not in the people. Miami looks the way it does, and Savannah the way it does, Paris the way it does, and New York City the way it does, and San Francisco the way it does, because of codes,”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;change the code and you change the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The New Urbanists were determined to undo the modernists’ work. They wrote a manifesto calling for compact, mixed-use, mixed-income neighborhoods of walkable street networks, with transit and attractive public spaces, all framed by buildings that responded to the local culture and climate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The greatest problem facing anyone who would repair sprawl remains the godlike power of code. Code is to the city what an operating system is to a computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the battle for American cities has moved from architectural drafting tables to the dense, arcane pages of the zoning codebooks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than totally replacing the county’s old code, it now runs alongside it: property developers can choose which code they wish to have applied to their project applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the imposition of the grid or any other plan from on high has another, ultimately more profound effect on the people who must inhabit it: it estranges them from the process of shaping their own world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;that great irony of the American city: a nation that celebrates freedom and weaves liberty into its national myth rarely gives regular people the chance to shape their own communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scant few neighborhoods in North America feature places that draw people together regularly for anything other than buying stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But nobody had fathomed just how deadly it was to be friendless. “We found, if you’re socially isolated, your risk for heat wave mortality goes up sevenfold,”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have made mistakes. We have been seduced by the wrong technologies. We gave up true freedom for the illusory promise of speed. We valued status over relationships. We tried to stamp out complexity instead of harnessing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We let the fear of being uncomfortable, inconvenienced, or hurt guide us into cities that not only isolate us but rob us of all the ease and pleasure and richness we might enjoy if the city were just a little bit more layered, a little bit more complex, a little bit messier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It dawned on Schmidt that the less money he made, the better his life was becoming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They realize that the happy city, the low carbon city, and the city that will save us are the same place, and that they have the wherewithal to create it. This is the truth that shines over the journey toward the happy city. We do not need to wait for someone else to make it. We build it when we choose how and where to live. We build it when we move a little bit closer. We build it when we choose to move a little slower. We build it by choosing to put aside our fear of the city and other people. We build the happy city by pursuing it in our own lives and, in so doing, pushing the city to change with us. We build it by living it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Charles Montgomery</name></author><summary type="html">I read this book just after reading Walkable City. Both of these have served as my introduction to urbanism and city planning. In addition to city planning this book is more broadly about human happiness and economics. In the United States, “economic growth” is dogma. Many believe the end of economic growth justify the means. But what is the point of economic growth if people generally unhappier and unhealthier? What if short-term econonomic growth in a quarter-by-quarter economy comes at the expense of long-term economic growth?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Walkable City</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/09/01/walkable_city.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Walkable City" /><published>2017-09-01T07:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-09-01T07:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2017/09/01/walkable_city</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2017/09/01/walkable_city.html">&lt;p&gt;This book, along with Happy City which I read just after this, was a real eye-opener for me. I enjoyed this book so much that immediately wanted to read more about city planning – thus, Happy City. Compared to Happy City, this book really makes the economic case for good urban planning. For better or worse this book comes across as anti-automobile. This will turn-off people who are very attached to their cars. However, for those open minded enough to see a better – or at least different way – car ownership is really self-defeating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;= = = = =
Quotes
= = = = =&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book is not about why cities work or how cities work, but about what works in cities. And what works best in the best cities is walkability. Walkability is both an end and a means, as well as a measure. While the physical and social rewards of walking are many, walkability is perhaps most useful as it contributes to urban vitality and most meaningful as an indicator of that vitality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get walkability right and so much of the rest will follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;whether intentionally or by accident, most American cities have effectively become no-walking zones. In the absence of any larger vision or mandate, city engineers—worshiping the twin gods of Smooth Traffic and Ample Parking—have turned our downtowns into places that are easy to get to but not worth arriving at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main thing that makes Rome—and the other winners: Venice, Boston, San Francisco, Barcelona, Amsterdam, Prague, Paris, and New York—so walkable is what we planners call “fabric,” the everyday collection of streets, blocks, and buildings that tie the monuments together. Despite its many technical failures, Rome’s fabric is superb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, there is more to walking than just making safe, pretty space for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The General Theory of Walkability explains how, to be favored, a walk has to satisfy four main conditions: it must be useful, safe, comfortable, and interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost 85 percent of money expended on cars and gas leaves the local economy22—much of it, of course, bound for the pockets of Middle Eastern princes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While transportation used to absorb only one-tenth of a typical family’s budget (1960), it now consumes more than one in five dollars spent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Particularly affected have been our children. While fully 50 percent walked to school in 1969, fewer than 15 percent do now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the mid-1970s, only about one in ten Americans was obese, which put us where much of Europe is right now. What has happened in the intervening thirty years is astonishing: by 2007, that rate had risen to one in three,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As recently as 1991, no states had adult obesity rates over 20 percent. By 2007, only one state, Colorado, was under 20 percent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Excessive weight now kills more Americans than smoking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Car crashes have killed over 3.2 million Americans, considerably more than all of our wars combined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the United States in 2004 suffered 14.5 traffic fatalities per 100,000 population, Germany, with its no-speed-limit autobahns, suffered only 7.1. Denmark rated a 6.8, Japan a 5.8, and the U.K. hit 5.3.27 And who beat them all? New York City, with a rate of 3.1. Indeed, since September 11, 2001, New York has saved more lives in traffic than it lost on 9/11.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If our entire country shared New York City’s traffic statistics, we would prevent more than twenty-four thousand deaths a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic theory held true: car crashes far outweighed murder by strangers as a cause of death in all locations and, in older cities like Pittsburgh, the inner cities were considerably safer overall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Closer to home, a Miami study found that “after driving their cars across the city for forty-five minutes, university students had higher blood pressure, higher heart rates, and lower frustration tolerance.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly, people with longer commutes report “lower satisfaction with life” than those who drive less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, the most green home (with Prius) in sprawl still loses out to the least green home in a walkable neighborhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“LEED architecture without good urban design is like cutting down the rainforest using hybrid-powered bulldozers.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;economist Ed Glaeser, who puts it this way: “We are a destructive species, and if you love nature, stay away from it. The best means of protecting the environment is to live in the heart of a city.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, New York consumes half the gasoline of Atlanta (326 versus 782 gallons per person per year). But Toronto cuts that number in half again, as does Sydney—and most European cities use only half as much as those places. Cut Europe’s number in half and you end up with Hong Kong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gold standard of quality-of-life rankings is the Mercer Survey, which carefully compares global cities in the ten categories of political stability, economics, social quality, health and sanitation, education, public services, recreation, consumer goods, housing, and climate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highest-rated American cities in 2010, which don’t appear until number 31, are Honolulu, San Francisco, Boston, Chicago, Washington, New York, and Seattle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Washington, D.C., is one of a handful of American cities that can accurately be described as car-optional. New York, Boston, Chicago, San Francisco, and not many others, provide an equivalent or better quality of life for the carless,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lewis Mumford declared that “our national flower is the concrete cloverleaf,”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;induced demand is the great intellectual black hole in city planning,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traffic studies are bullshit. They are bullshit for three main reasons: First: The computer model is only as good as its inputs, and there’s nothing easier than tweaking the inputs to get the outcome you want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second: Traffic studies are typically performed by firms that do traffic engineering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;guess who gets the big contract for the roadway expansion that the study deems necessary?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, and most essentially: The main problem with traffic studies is that they almost never consider the phenomenon of induced demand. Induced demand is the name for what happens when increasing the supply of roadways lowers the time cost of driving, causing more people to drive and obliterating any reductions in congestion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The metro area with the highest estimated road building cost was Nashville, Tennessee with a price tag of $3,243 per family per year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;congestion actually saves fuel—and ultimately is one of the only things that does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everybody likes Jane Jacobs, right? She was famous for fighting traffic engineers, and took them to task repeatedly and effectively in her masterpiece, The Death and Life of Great American Cities. Most planners and many public servants swear by that book, but few have read Dark Age Ahead, in which, forty years later, she took off the gloves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond giving new life to the areas previously blighted by the highways, these road removals have actually been found to reduce overall travel times within their cities. The most celebrated, and properly so, has got to be the Cheonggyecheon (pronounced chung-yay-chun) Freeway in Seoul, where a traffic-choked elevated expressway was hauled down in the mid-2000s, daylighting the river that it had obscured for half a century.25&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would seem that only one thing is more destructive to the health of our downtowns than welcoming cars unconditionally and that is getting rid of them entirely. The proper response to obesity is not to stop eating, and most stores need car traffic to survive. With autos reintroduced, most failed pedestrian malls, like Monroe Place in Grand Rapids, have come back at least partway. The key is to welcome cars in the proper number and at the proper speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mayor Ken Livingstone proposed the only known cure, economics. Against “a massive and sustained media campaign,”36 he introduced a roughly fifteen-dollar fee for any driver who wanted to enter the congested heart of the city on weekdays, with the revenue to be used to support a progressive transportation agenda. Here’s what happened: Congestion dropped 30 percent in the toll zone, and typical journey times went down by 14 percent. Cycling among Londoners jumped 20 percent and air pollution fell about 12 percent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ivan Illich, the multinational intellectual who in 1973 wrote the smartest thing that I have yet to read about transportation: “Beyond a certain speed, motorized vehicles create remoteness which they alone can shrink. They create distances for all and shrink them for only a few.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is remarkable. Compared to our colonial ancestors, we throw 25 percent more of our national and personal resources into transportation and we ultimately move no faster. But we do move farther,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Illich discovered a hidden physical law: the faster a society moves, the more it spreads out and the more time it must spend moving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parking covers more acres of urban America than any other one thing3—just look at an aerial photo of downtown Houston—&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than parking working in the service of cities, cities have been working in the service of parking, almost entirely to their detriment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step to understanding how parking works is to get a grasp of how much it costs and who pays for it. Because it is so plentiful and often free to use, it is easy to imagine that it costs very little.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cheapest urban parking space in America, an 8½-by-18-foot piece of asphalt on relatively worthless land, costs about four thousand dollars to create—and not much urban land is worthless. The most expensive parking space, in an underground parking garage, can cost forty thousand dollars or more to build.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In between those extremes is the standard aboveground urban parking structure, which can usually be built for between twenty and thirty thousand dollars per space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2010, the first nationwide count determined that there are half a billion empty parking spaces in America at any given time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When parking is no longer the exclusive property of an individual business, it becomes much more efficient. A space that serves an office during the day can serve a restaurant in the evening and a resident overnight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is, Americans require parking and limit density, while Europeans require density and limit parking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With rare exceptions, every transit trip begins and ends with a walk. As a result, while walkability benefits from good transit, good transit relies absolutely on walkability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roughly a third of Washingtonians and San Franciscans take transit to work, and the majority of New Yorkers do. Perennial sprawl stars like Jacksonville and Nashville, on the other hand, hover below 2 percent, no matter how you measure them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to America’s Finest News Source, The Onion, “98 percent of U.S. commuters favor public transportation for others.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He determined that each resident of the seven high-quality cities paid roughly $370 more per year for public transportation than a resident of the other forty-three, but saved $1,040 in vehicle, parking, and road costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A true neighborhood has a center and an edge, and contains a wide variety of activities in close proximity within an armature of pedestrian-friendly streets and public spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way to reduce traffic is to reduce roads or to increase the cost of using them, and that is a bitter pill that few pro-transit cities are ready to swallow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And without true walkability on both ends of the line, your system is a nonstarter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your goals are efficiency and pleasure, rail beats bus hands down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recognizing that only 5 percent of pedestrian collisions at twenty miles per hour result in death, versus 85 percent at forty mph,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What makes a sidewalk safe is not its width, but whether it is protected by a line of parked cars that form a barrier of steel between the pedestrian and the roadway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other way that cities increase traffic flow at the expense of pedestrians is with the “right on red” rule. God knows, I love this as a driver, but, as Jan Gehl puts it, “the widespread American practice of allowing cars to ‘turn right on red’ at intersections is unthinkable in cities that want to invite people to walk and bicycle.”27 It is banned in the Netherlands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;cycling has got to be the most efficient, healthful, empowering, and sustainable form of transportation there is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Closer to home, and supposedly part of America, the most bike friendly of our sizeable cities has got to be Portland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pedaling Revolution—the seminal book on urban cycling—&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the regular cyclists were as fit as the noncyclists ten years younger&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From an ecological perspective, then, most U.S. cities offer too much grassland and too little forest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get the design right and people will walk in almost any climate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This error points the way to the first question to ask before investing in walkability: where can spending the least money make the most difference?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jeff Speck</name></author><summary type="html">This book, along with Happy City which I read just after this, was a real eye-opener for me. I enjoyed this book so much that immediately wanted to read more about city planning – thus, Happy City. Compared to Happy City, this book really makes the economic case for good urban planning. For better or worse this book comes across as anti-automobile. This will turn-off people who are very attached to their cars. However, for those open minded enough to see a better – or at least different way – car ownership is really self-defeating.</summary></entry></feed>