<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-12-30T11:15:45-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Sam Rysdyk</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">Happy City</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/books/2017/10/01/happy_cities/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Happy City" /><published>2017-10-01T07:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-10-01T07:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/books/2017/10/01/happy_cities</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/books/2017/10/01/happy_cities/">&lt;p&gt;I read this book just after reading Walkable City. Both of these have served as my introduction to urbanism and city planning. In addition to city planning this book is more broadly about human happiness and economics. In the United States, “economic growth” is dogma. Many believe the end of economic growth justify the means. But what is the point of economic growth if people generally unhappier and unhealthier? What if short-term econonomic growth in a quarter-by-quarter economy comes at the expense of long-term economic growth?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;= = = = =
Quotes
= = = = =&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dream of riches, Peñalosa complained, served only to make Bogotans feel bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peñalosa promised neither a car in every garage nor a socialist revolution. His promise was simple. He was going to make Bogotans happier. “And what are our needs for happiness?” he asked. “We need to walk, just as birds need to fly. We need to be around other people. We need beauty. We need contact with nature. And most of all, we need not to be excluded. We need to feel some sort of equality.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a gospel of transformative urbanism. The city itself could be a device for happiness. Life could be improved, even amid economic doldrums, by changing the shapes and systems that defined urban existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peñalosa’s first and most defining act as mayor was to declare war: not on crime or drugs or poverty, but on private cars. “A city can be friendly to people or it can be friendly to cars, but it can’t be both,” he announced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the third year of his term Peñalosa challenged Bogotans to participate in an experiment, a día sin carro. As of dawn on February 24, 2000, all private cars were banned from city streets for the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was the first day in four years that nobody was killed in traffic. Hospital admissions fell by almost a third. The toxic haze over the city thinned. People still got to work, and schools reported normal attendance. Bogotans enjoyed the day so much that they voted to make it a yearly affair, and to ban all private cars during rush hour every day by 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The urban shake-up that began with the mortgage crisis in 2008 hit the newest, shiniest, most sprawling parts of the American city the hardest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sprawl city requires cheap energy, cheap land, and cheap materials, and the days of cheap are over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A man could achieve pure happiness only by reaching the height of his potential, and that meant not just thinking virtuously but behaving virtuously too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adam Smith warned that it was a deception to believe that wealth and comfort alone would bring happiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He found that people who claimed to be happy tended to have more blood flowing to that left prefrontal region than to the right side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of all the ways they passed their days, having sex made the women happiest of all, with socializing coming a close second. What made them least happy? Commuting to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside Disneyland, even today, every architectural detail, every view, every transportation experience, every sensation—right down to the texture of the pavement and the scent of the air—was designed with the express purpose of tipping the hedonic scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are left with the question of authenticity: If you’re happy, does reality matter?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People who are well educated rate their happiness higher than those who aren’t. Employed people are happier than unemployed people—&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life satisfaction is strongly influenced by location.* People in small towns are generally happier than people who live in big cities. People who live next to the ocean report being happier than those who don’t. Living under the flight path of commuter jets is terrible for happiness. Persistent wind is bad, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;when it comes to life satisfaction, relationships with other people beat income, hands down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just going from being friendless to having one friend or family member to confide in had the same effect on life satisfaction as a tripling of income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our trust in neighbors, police, governments, and even total strangers has a huge influence on happiness—again, much more than income does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;cities must be regarded as more than engines of wealth; they must be viewed as systems that should be shaped to improve human well-being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For every new urban plaza, starchitect-designed tower, or sleek new light-rail network, there are a hundred thousand cul-de-sacs out in the dispersed city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, the dispersed city is the most expensive, resource-intense, land-gobbling, polluting way of living ever built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The average exurban family needs at least one more car than do families who live close to where they work, shop, study, and play. That family also spends twice as much just getting around in order to meet its daily needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(It’s also a reason that the farther a house was from a vibrant city center, the more likely it was to experience foreclosure during the crash,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investing in a detached home on the urban edge is like gambling on oil futures and global geopolitics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As much as we complain about other people, there is nothing worse for mental health than a social desert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;cities. A Swedish study found that people who endure more than a forty-five-minute commute were 40 percent more likely to divorce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People’s new homes were so big that they created a whole new layer of housekeeping, and so expensive that they forced their owners to work harder to keep them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans do not perceive the value of things in absolute terms. We never have. Just as our eyes process the color and luminosity of an object relative to its surroundings, the brain constantly adjusts its idea of what we need in order to be happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have been hardwired for active dissatisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, Stutzer and Frey found that a person with a one-hour commute has to earn 40 percent more money to be as satisfied with life as someone who walks to the office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quick: Which would make you happier—living in California or the U.S. Midwest?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Californians and midwesterners report pretty much the same level of life satisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest danger is, by its nature, the least exciting. It is the sickness that comes from doing nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;aside from sedentary Saudi Arabians and some South Pacific Islanders, Americans are now the fattest people on the planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;killer drivers are so common in sprawl that the carnage they create far exceeds the damage done by killers who use other weapons. In fact, someone who walks out her door on the edges of sprawl suburbia is much more likely to die at the hands of a stranger than someone moving through most American central cities or inner suburbs. The only difference is that most of suburbia’s killers didn’t mean it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s an image that sticks: imagine a loaded Boeing 747 crashing every three days, killing everyone aboard. That’s how many people die on U.S. highways every year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;rational actor would be terrified of suburban roads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result: drivers kill four times as many pedestrians on spacious suburban residential streets than on the narrow streets of traditional neighborhoods, because those spacious roads make driving faster feel safer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is not collisions that kill people, but collisions at high speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A pedestrian hit by a car going 35 miles per hour is ten times as likely to die than if he was hit by a car going 25 miles per hour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The average time it takes for new urban highway capacity to fill up with new demand? Five to six years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are using so much of the earth’s raw material that we are dooming future generations to poverty and hardship. It would take nine planets to supply all we needed if everyone ate, built, traveled, and threw stuff away as Americans do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On average, suburbanites pump out about twice the greenhouse gas emissions of people living in dense city centers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;people who live in areas with more parks are more helpful and trusting than people who don’t, regardless of their income or race. Nature is not merely good for us. It brings out the good in us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is crucial for healthy living, she insists, is not quantity, but regular exposure, daily doses of nature. So the trick is in finding ways to infuse nature, and nature complexity, into denser places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That made Vancouver the only major city in North America without a single highway running through its core.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of what made Vancouver’s vertical experiment both unique and desirable was the way it accommodated residents’ biophilic needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One big park won’t do. “We can’t just build Central Park and say, ‘Well, we’re done,’” Kuo insisted. “Nature has to be part of your life. It has to be part of your daily habitat and routine.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you search hard enough for places that balance our competing needs for privacy, nature, conviviality, and convenience, you end up with a hybrid, somewhere between the vertical and horizontal city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the Second World War, the capital of Denmark had embraced dispersal as fervently as any American city. Everyone bought a car, and suburbs spilled out from the city’s medieval heart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We found that if you make more road space, you get more cars. If you make more bike lanes, you get more bikes. If you make more space for people, you get more people and of course then you get public life.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tellingly, the word community is increasingly used to refer to groups of people who use the same media or who happen to like a certain product, regardless of whether its members have actually met.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Television, that great window to the world, has been an unequivocal disaster for happiness. The more TV you watch, the fewer friendships you are likely to have, the less trusting you become, and the less happy you are likely to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;every urban landscape is a collection of memory- and emotion-activating symbols.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Human bones have evolved to withstand impact with hard surfaces up to a speed of about twenty miles per hour, which is faster than a reasonably fit person can run.* So it is natural to get anxious when confronted with hard objects moving faster than that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Participants begin to ask what streets are for, and they invariably seize upon the answer that Copenhageners found decades ago: streets are for whatever we decide they are for, and central cities need not accept the discomforts thrust on them by dispersal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No wonder four in ten Americans actually claim to love their cars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One group of commuters reports enjoying themselves more than everyone else. Their route to happy mobility is simple. These are people who travel on their own steam like Robert Judge. They walk. They run. They ride bicycles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why would traveling more slowly and using more effort offer more satisfaction than driving? Part of the answer exists in basic human physiology. We were born to move—not merely to be transported,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The psychologist has devoted his life to the study of human moods. In test after test he proved that the most powerful way to fix a dark mood is simply to take a brisk walk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can literally walk ourselves into a state of well-being. The same is true of cycling,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bicycle can expand the self-propelled travelers’ geographical reach by an astounding nine or sixteen times. Quite simply, a human on a bicycle is the most efficient traveler among all machines and animals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Few places design travel behavior as powerfully as Atlanta. The average working adult in Atlanta’s suburbs now drives forty-four miles a day.† Ninety-four percent of Atlantans commute by car.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surveys in the United States and Canada reveal that transit riders are the most miserable commuters of all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s just that decades of underinvestment mean that the typical transit journey is crowded, slow, uncertain, or uncomfortable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;administrators typically choose the most utilitarian-looking materials for bus interiors and stations—even when attractive finishes are no more expensive—simply to avoid the appearance of having wasted money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Geller and his colleagues set out to create a network of “low-stress” bikeways that either physically separated cyclists from cars or slowed cars down past the speed of fear on shared routes. It worked. Commuting by bike more than doubled in Portland between 2000 and 2008.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is where equity and efficiency collide: because of their light footprint, infrastructure for walkers and cyclists costs only a tiny fraction of auto infrastructure to build and maintain. So cyclists and pedestrian commuters who pay property and income tax actually end up subsidizing their car-driving neighbors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the fair city, people who share space on transit enjoy the right-of-way on congested roads. In the fair city, streets are safe for everyone, especially children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the fair city, everyone has access to parks, shops, services, and healthy food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The happy city plan is an energy plan. It is a climate plan. It is a belt-tightening plan for cash-strapped cities. It is also an economic plan, a jobs plan, and a corrective for weak systems. It is a plan for resilience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I realized that the power that shapes our city is in the code, not in the people. Miami looks the way it does, and Savannah the way it does, Paris the way it does, and New York City the way it does, and San Francisco the way it does, because of codes,”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;change the code and you change the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The New Urbanists were determined to undo the modernists’ work. They wrote a manifesto calling for compact, mixed-use, mixed-income neighborhoods of walkable street networks, with transit and attractive public spaces, all framed by buildings that responded to the local culture and climate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The greatest problem facing anyone who would repair sprawl remains the godlike power of code. Code is to the city what an operating system is to a computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the battle for American cities has moved from architectural drafting tables to the dense, arcane pages of the zoning codebooks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than totally replacing the county’s old code, it now runs alongside it: property developers can choose which code they wish to have applied to their project applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the imposition of the grid or any other plan from on high has another, ultimately more profound effect on the people who must inhabit it: it estranges them from the process of shaping their own world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;that great irony of the American city: a nation that celebrates freedom and weaves liberty into its national myth rarely gives regular people the chance to shape their own communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scant few neighborhoods in North America feature places that draw people together regularly for anything other than buying stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But nobody had fathomed just how deadly it was to be friendless. “We found, if you’re socially isolated, your risk for heat wave mortality goes up sevenfold,”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have made mistakes. We have been seduced by the wrong technologies. We gave up true freedom for the illusory promise of speed. We valued status over relationships. We tried to stamp out complexity instead of harnessing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We let the fear of being uncomfortable, inconvenienced, or hurt guide us into cities that not only isolate us but rob us of all the ease and pleasure and richness we might enjoy if the city were just a little bit more layered, a little bit more complex, a little bit messier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It dawned on Schmidt that the less money he made, the better his life was becoming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They realize that the happy city, the low carbon city, and the city that will save us are the same place, and that they have the wherewithal to create it. This is the truth that shines over the journey toward the happy city. We do not need to wait for someone else to make it. We build it when we choose how and where to live. We build it when we move a little bit closer. We build it when we choose to move a little slower. We build it by choosing to put aside our fear of the city and other people. We build the happy city by pursuing it in our own lives and, in so doing, pushing the city to change with us. We build it by living it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Charles Montgomery</name></author><summary type="html">I read this book just after reading Walkable City. Both of these have served as my introduction to urbanism and city planning. In addition to city planning this book is more broadly about human happiness and economics. In the United States, “economic growth” is dogma. Many believe the end of economic growth justify the means. But what is the point of economic growth if people generally unhappier and unhealthier? What if short-term econonomic growth in a quarter-by-quarter economy comes at the expense of long-term economic growth?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Walkable City</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/books/2017/09/01/walkable_city/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Walkable City" /><published>2017-09-01T07:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-09-01T07:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/books/2017/09/01/walkable_city</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/books/2017/09/01/walkable_city/">&lt;p&gt;This book, along with Happy City which I read just after this, was a real eye-opener for me. I enjoyed this book so much that immediately wanted to read more about city planning – thus, Happy City. Compared to Happy City, this book really makes the economic case for good urban planning. For better or worse this book comes across as anti-automobile. This will turn-off people who are very attached to their cars. However, for those open minded enough to see a better – or at least different way – car ownership is really self-defeating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;= = = = =
Quotes
= = = = =&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book is not about why cities work or how cities work, but about what works in cities. And what works best in the best cities is walkability. Walkability is both an end and a means, as well as a measure. While the physical and social rewards of walking are many, walkability is perhaps most useful as it contributes to urban vitality and most meaningful as an indicator of that vitality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get walkability right and so much of the rest will follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;whether intentionally or by accident, most American cities have effectively become no-walking zones. In the absence of any larger vision or mandate, city engineers—worshiping the twin gods of Smooth Traffic and Ample Parking—have turned our downtowns into places that are easy to get to but not worth arriving at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main thing that makes Rome—and the other winners: Venice, Boston, San Francisco, Barcelona, Amsterdam, Prague, Paris, and New York—so walkable is what we planners call “fabric,” the everyday collection of streets, blocks, and buildings that tie the monuments together. Despite its many technical failures, Rome’s fabric is superb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, there is more to walking than just making safe, pretty space for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The General Theory of Walkability explains how, to be favored, a walk has to satisfy four main conditions: it must be useful, safe, comfortable, and interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost 85 percent of money expended on cars and gas leaves the local economy22—much of it, of course, bound for the pockets of Middle Eastern princes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While transportation used to absorb only one-tenth of a typical family’s budget (1960), it now consumes more than one in five dollars spent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Particularly affected have been our children. While fully 50 percent walked to school in 1969, fewer than 15 percent do now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the mid-1970s, only about one in ten Americans was obese, which put us where much of Europe is right now. What has happened in the intervening thirty years is astonishing: by 2007, that rate had risen to one in three,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As recently as 1991, no states had adult obesity rates over 20 percent. By 2007, only one state, Colorado, was under 20 percent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Excessive weight now kills more Americans than smoking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Car crashes have killed over 3.2 million Americans, considerably more than all of our wars combined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the United States in 2004 suffered 14.5 traffic fatalities per 100,000 population, Germany, with its no-speed-limit autobahns, suffered only 7.1. Denmark rated a 6.8, Japan a 5.8, and the U.K. hit 5.3.27 And who beat them all? New York City, with a rate of 3.1. Indeed, since September 11, 2001, New York has saved more lives in traffic than it lost on 9/11.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If our entire country shared New York City’s traffic statistics, we would prevent more than twenty-four thousand deaths a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic theory held true: car crashes far outweighed murder by strangers as a cause of death in all locations and, in older cities like Pittsburgh, the inner cities were considerably safer overall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Closer to home, a Miami study found that “after driving their cars across the city for forty-five minutes, university students had higher blood pressure, higher heart rates, and lower frustration tolerance.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly, people with longer commutes report “lower satisfaction with life” than those who drive less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, the most green home (with Prius) in sprawl still loses out to the least green home in a walkable neighborhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“LEED architecture without good urban design is like cutting down the rainforest using hybrid-powered bulldozers.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;economist Ed Glaeser, who puts it this way: “We are a destructive species, and if you love nature, stay away from it. The best means of protecting the environment is to live in the heart of a city.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, New York consumes half the gasoline of Atlanta (326 versus 782 gallons per person per year). But Toronto cuts that number in half again, as does Sydney—and most European cities use only half as much as those places. Cut Europe’s number in half and you end up with Hong Kong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gold standard of quality-of-life rankings is the Mercer Survey, which carefully compares global cities in the ten categories of political stability, economics, social quality, health and sanitation, education, public services, recreation, consumer goods, housing, and climate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highest-rated American cities in 2010, which don’t appear until number 31, are Honolulu, San Francisco, Boston, Chicago, Washington, New York, and Seattle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Washington, D.C., is one of a handful of American cities that can accurately be described as car-optional. New York, Boston, Chicago, San Francisco, and not many others, provide an equivalent or better quality of life for the carless,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lewis Mumford declared that “our national flower is the concrete cloverleaf,”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;induced demand is the great intellectual black hole in city planning,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traffic studies are bullshit. They are bullshit for three main reasons: First: The computer model is only as good as its inputs, and there’s nothing easier than tweaking the inputs to get the outcome you want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second: Traffic studies are typically performed by firms that do traffic engineering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;guess who gets the big contract for the roadway expansion that the study deems necessary?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, and most essentially: The main problem with traffic studies is that they almost never consider the phenomenon of induced demand. Induced demand is the name for what happens when increasing the supply of roadways lowers the time cost of driving, causing more people to drive and obliterating any reductions in congestion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The metro area with the highest estimated road building cost was Nashville, Tennessee with a price tag of $3,243 per family per year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;congestion actually saves fuel—and ultimately is one of the only things that does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everybody likes Jane Jacobs, right? She was famous for fighting traffic engineers, and took them to task repeatedly and effectively in her masterpiece, The Death and Life of Great American Cities. Most planners and many public servants swear by that book, but few have read Dark Age Ahead, in which, forty years later, she took off the gloves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond giving new life to the areas previously blighted by the highways, these road removals have actually been found to reduce overall travel times within their cities. The most celebrated, and properly so, has got to be the Cheonggyecheon (pronounced chung-yay-chun) Freeway in Seoul, where a traffic-choked elevated expressway was hauled down in the mid-2000s, daylighting the river that it had obscured for half a century.25&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would seem that only one thing is more destructive to the health of our downtowns than welcoming cars unconditionally and that is getting rid of them entirely. The proper response to obesity is not to stop eating, and most stores need car traffic to survive. With autos reintroduced, most failed pedestrian malls, like Monroe Place in Grand Rapids, have come back at least partway. The key is to welcome cars in the proper number and at the proper speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mayor Ken Livingstone proposed the only known cure, economics. Against “a massive and sustained media campaign,”36 he introduced a roughly fifteen-dollar fee for any driver who wanted to enter the congested heart of the city on weekdays, with the revenue to be used to support a progressive transportation agenda. Here’s what happened: Congestion dropped 30 percent in the toll zone, and typical journey times went down by 14 percent. Cycling among Londoners jumped 20 percent and air pollution fell about 12 percent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ivan Illich, the multinational intellectual who in 1973 wrote the smartest thing that I have yet to read about transportation: “Beyond a certain speed, motorized vehicles create remoteness which they alone can shrink. They create distances for all and shrink them for only a few.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is remarkable. Compared to our colonial ancestors, we throw 25 percent more of our national and personal resources into transportation and we ultimately move no faster. But we do move farther,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Illich discovered a hidden physical law: the faster a society moves, the more it spreads out and the more time it must spend moving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parking covers more acres of urban America than any other one thing3—just look at an aerial photo of downtown Houston—&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than parking working in the service of cities, cities have been working in the service of parking, almost entirely to their detriment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step to understanding how parking works is to get a grasp of how much it costs and who pays for it. Because it is so plentiful and often free to use, it is easy to imagine that it costs very little.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cheapest urban parking space in America, an 8½-by-18-foot piece of asphalt on relatively worthless land, costs about four thousand dollars to create—and not much urban land is worthless. The most expensive parking space, in an underground parking garage, can cost forty thousand dollars or more to build.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In between those extremes is the standard aboveground urban parking structure, which can usually be built for between twenty and thirty thousand dollars per space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2010, the first nationwide count determined that there are half a billion empty parking spaces in America at any given time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When parking is no longer the exclusive property of an individual business, it becomes much more efficient. A space that serves an office during the day can serve a restaurant in the evening and a resident overnight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is, Americans require parking and limit density, while Europeans require density and limit parking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With rare exceptions, every transit trip begins and ends with a walk. As a result, while walkability benefits from good transit, good transit relies absolutely on walkability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roughly a third of Washingtonians and San Franciscans take transit to work, and the majority of New Yorkers do. Perennial sprawl stars like Jacksonville and Nashville, on the other hand, hover below 2 percent, no matter how you measure them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to America’s Finest News Source, The Onion, “98 percent of U.S. commuters favor public transportation for others.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He determined that each resident of the seven high-quality cities paid roughly $370 more per year for public transportation than a resident of the other forty-three, but saved $1,040 in vehicle, parking, and road costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A true neighborhood has a center and an edge, and contains a wide variety of activities in close proximity within an armature of pedestrian-friendly streets and public spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way to reduce traffic is to reduce roads or to increase the cost of using them, and that is a bitter pill that few pro-transit cities are ready to swallow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And without true walkability on both ends of the line, your system is a nonstarter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your goals are efficiency and pleasure, rail beats bus hands down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recognizing that only 5 percent of pedestrian collisions at twenty miles per hour result in death, versus 85 percent at forty mph,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What makes a sidewalk safe is not its width, but whether it is protected by a line of parked cars that form a barrier of steel between the pedestrian and the roadway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other way that cities increase traffic flow at the expense of pedestrians is with the “right on red” rule. God knows, I love this as a driver, but, as Jan Gehl puts it, “the widespread American practice of allowing cars to ‘turn right on red’ at intersections is unthinkable in cities that want to invite people to walk and bicycle.”27 It is banned in the Netherlands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;cycling has got to be the most efficient, healthful, empowering, and sustainable form of transportation there is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Closer to home, and supposedly part of America, the most bike friendly of our sizeable cities has got to be Portland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pedaling Revolution—the seminal book on urban cycling—&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the regular cyclists were as fit as the noncyclists ten years younger&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From an ecological perspective, then, most U.S. cities offer too much grassland and too little forest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get the design right and people will walk in almost any climate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This error points the way to the first question to ask before investing in walkability: where can spending the least money make the most difference?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jeff Speck</name></author><summary type="html">This book, along with Happy City which I read just after this, was a real eye-opener for me. I enjoyed this book so much that immediately wanted to read more about city planning – thus, Happy City. Compared to Happy City, this book really makes the economic case for good urban planning. For better or worse this book comes across as anti-automobile. This will turn-off people who are very attached to their cars. However, for those open minded enough to see a better – or at least different way – car ownership is really self-defeating.</summary></entry></feed>